I want to address the issue of compassion.
أريد ان اتحدث عن التعاطف ..
Compassion has many faces.
التعاطف له اوجه كثيرة
Some of them are fierce; some of them are wrathful;
احيانا يعد من القسوة .., احيانا يعد من الاساسيات
some of them are tender; some of them are wise.
احيانا يعد من التسامح واحيانا من الذكاء
A line that the Dalai Lama once said,
وبعبارة الدلالي لاما كما قال يوماً
he said, "Love and compassion are necessities.
الحب و التعاطف هما من اساسيات الحياة
They are not luxuries.
لا من رفاهيتها
Without them,
وبدون الحب و التعاطف
humanity cannot survive."
لا يمكن للبشرية الاستمرار
And I would suggest,
وانا اريد ان اقول
it is not only humanity that won't survive,
انها ليست البشرية فحسب
but it is all species on the planet,
ولكن كل الفصائل على هذا الكوكب لايمكنها العيش بدون الحب والتعاطف
as we've heard today.
كما سمعنا اليوم
It is the big cats,
فالعاطفة موجودة بين فصيل الاسود
and it's the plankton.
وبين البلانكتونات
Two weeks ago, I was in Bangalore in India.
منذ اسبوعين كنت في بانغلور في الهند
I was so privileged
لقد كنت محظوظة
to be able to teach in a hospice
بأن استطعت ان ادرس في دير
on the outskirts of Bangalore.
في ضواحي بانغلور
And early in the morning,
ففي الصباح الباكر
I went into the ward.
كنت أزور الجناح الخاص بالمعدمين
In that hospice,
في ذلك الدير
there were 31 men and women
وكان هناك 31 رجلا و امرأة
who were actively dying.
على أعتاب الموت
And I walked up to the bedside
لقد سرت بقرب سرير
of an old woman
لإمرأة عجوز
who was breathing very rapidly, fragile,
والتي كانت تتنفس بصعوبة بالغة
obviously in the latter phase
وكانت كما يبدو لي في مرحلة الحياة الاخيرة
of active dying.
من الموت البطيء
I looked into her face.
نظرت الى وجهها
I looked into the face
نظرت الى وجه
of her son sitting next to her,
ابنها القابع بقربها
and his face was just riven
والذي كان - وجهه - مليئاً
with grief and confusion.
بالحزن والحيرة
And I remembered
وتذكرت حينها
a line from the Mahabharata,
عبارة من " ماهابهارتا "
the great Indian epic:
وهي ملحمة هندية شهيرة حيث ذكر فيها
"What is the most wondrous thing in the world, Yudhisthira?"
" ما هو أعجب شئ في العالم ، يا "يودهيسثيرا" ؟.
And Yudhisthira replied,
فأجاب يودهيسثيرا
"The most wondrous thing in the world
"ان أعجب عجائب الدنيا هي كل شيء
is that all around us
يحيط بنا
people can be dying
ان الناس تموت من حولنا
and we don't realize
ونحن لا ندرك
it can happen to us."
اننا سنواجه هذا الموت ذات يوم "
I looked up.
لقد نظرت
Tending those 31 dying people
نحو ال31 شخصاً هؤلاء والذين كانوا يواجهون الموت
were young women
لقد كان من بينهم نسوة صغيرات في العمر
from villages around Bangalore.
من قرى محيطة بانغلور
I looked into the face of one of these women,
لقد نظرت الى اوجه هؤلاء النسوة
and I saw in her face
ورأيت في وجوههن
the strength that arises
القوة التي نتجت
when natural compassion is really present.
عن وجود التعاطف الحقيقي حولهم
I watched her hands
لقد رأيت الأيدي وهي
as she bathed an old man.
تقوم بغسل اجساد الرجال الهرمين في العمر
My gaze went to another young woman
ثم شد إهتمامي إمرأة
as she wiped the face
كانت قد صفعت
of another dying person.
وجه رجلٌ يواجه الموت
And it reminded me
وذكرني هذا
of something that I had just been present for.
بشيء كنت قد صادفته من قبل
Every year or so,
تقريبا كل عام
I have the privilege of taking clinicians
كان يساورني الحظ ان اخرج في مهمات
into the Himalayas and the Tibetan Plateau.
الى جبال الهملايا و التيبت
And we run clinics
وكنا ندير عيادات
in these very remote regions
في تلك المناطق النائية
where there's no medical care whatsoever.
والتي كانت تفتقر للتغطية الصحية تماما
And on the first day at Simikot in Humla,
وفي اول يوم في " سيميكوت " في " هوملا "
far west of Nepal,
في غرب النيبال
the most impoverished region of Nepal,
المنطقة الأفقر في نيبال
an old man came in
جاء رجل هرم في العمر
clutching a bundle of rags.
ممسكاً بيده مجموعة من الخرق
And he walked in, and somebody said something to him,
ودخل علينا .. فقال له أحدٌ شيئاً لم يفهمه
we realized he was deaf,
فأدركنا انه أصم
and we looked into the rags,
وعندما نظرنا الى الخرق
and there was this pair of eyes.
رأينا عينين ..
The rags were unwrapped
عندما ألزلنا الخرق
from a little girl
وجدنا فتاة صغيرة ..
whose body was massively burned.
كانت محروقة الجسد بصورة بالغة
Again,
مرة أخرى ..
the eyes and hands
كانت عيني و يدي
of Avalokiteshvara.
" أفالوكيتشفارا "
It was the young women, the health aids,
انها الإمرأة الشابة المساعدة الطبية
who cleaned the wounds of this baby
والتي تنظف جروح هذه الطفلة ..
and dressed the wounds.
وتُغطي الجروح
I know those hands and eyes;
انا أعرف هذه الأيدي والأعين
they touched me as well.
لقد لامست روحي
They touched me at that time.
لامست روحي في تلك الاثناء
They have touched me throughout my 68 years.
واستمرت تلهمني طيلة سنوات عمري ال68
They touched me when I was four
لقد لامست روحي عندما كنت في الرابعة من العمر
and I lost my eyesight
لقد فقدت بصري حينها
and was partially paralyzed.
واصبت بشلل جزئي
And my family brought in
وقامت عائلتي بجلب إمرأة
a woman whose mother had been a slave
كانت إبنة لإمرأة " مستعبدة "
to take care of me.
لكي تهتم بي
And that woman
وتلك المرأة
did not have sentimental compassion.
لم تكن تملك التعاطف الوجداني
She had phenomenal strength.
وكانت تملك قوة استثنائية
And it was really her strength, I believe,
وانا اعتقد ان قوتها
that became the kind of mudra and imprimatur
هي التي كانت تحيط بي وترافقني
that has been a guiding light in my life.
وتوجهني وتنير دربي طيلة حياتي
So we can ask:
لذا يمكننا أن نتسائل
What is compassion comprised of?
مما يتألف التعاطف ؟
And there are various facets.
هناك الكثير من الاوجه ..
And there's referential and non-referential compassion.
بعضها له تأصيل علمي .. والآخر لا تأصيل له
But first, compassion is comprised
بداية التعاطف مكون
of that capacity
من القدرة على
to see clearly
أن ترى بوضوح تام
into the nature of suffering.
طبيعة المعاناة من حولك
It is that ability
انها القدرة
to really stand strong
على ان تقف برباطة جأش
and to recognize also
وان تميز أيضاً
that I'm not separate from this suffering.
انك لست منفصلاً عن تلك المعاناة
But that is not enough,
ولكن هذا ليس كافياً
because compassion,
لأن التعاطف
which activates the motor cortex,
يفعّل الدماغ
means that we aspire,
انه يعني الطموح ..
we actually aspire to transform suffering.
و أن نطمح لتغيير معاناة الآخرين
And if we're so blessed,
وان كنا مباركين ..
we engage in activities
فاننا سوف ننخرط بأنشطة
that transform suffering.
يمكنها ان تُنهي تلك المعاناة
But compassion has another component,
ولكن للتعاطف مكون آخر
and that component is really essential.
وهذا المكون أساسيٌ جداً
That component
ان ذلك المكون
is that we cannot be attached to outcome.
اننا لا نستطيع أن نرتبط بالنتائج
Now I worked with dying people
فأنا قد عملت مع أشخاص يواجهون الموت
for over 40 years.
لمدة 40 عاماً
I had the privilege of working on death row
لقد كنت محظوظة بأن اعمل في زنزانات المحكومين بالاعدام
in a maximum security [prison] for six years.
في السجون مُحكمة الحراسة لمدة ستة سنوات
And I realized so clearly
لقد تبين لي بوضوح
in bringing my own life experience,
ان استحضار اي تجربة سابقة
from working with dying people
من العمل مع الاشخاص على عتبة الموت
and training caregivers,
وتدريب المعدمين
that any attachment to outcome
والتي يمكن ان تجعلني اتوقع نتائج معينة
would distort deeply
سوف يقوض قدرتي تماما
my own capacity to be fully present
على ان اكون حاضرة تماما في
to the whole catastrophe.
كل حالة و أزمة ومصيبة على حدى
And when I worked in the prison system,
وعندما عملت داخل السجون
it was so clear to me, this:
كان من الجلي بالنسبة لي
that many of us
ان كثيرون منا
in this room,
في هذه القاعة
and almost all of the men that I worked with on death row,
وكل من عملت معه في زنزانات الموت ..
the seeds of their own compassion had never been watered.
نعاني من عدم رعاية بذرة التعاطف لدينا
That compassion is actually
ان التعاطف في الحقيقة
an inherent human quality.
صفة انسانية متأصلة
It is there within every human being.
انها موجودة في كل إنسان
But the conditions
ولكن الظروف هي التي
for compassion to be activated,
تحفز خاصية التعاطف
to be aroused,
وتثيرها
are particular conditions.
الى حالات ومستويات معينة
I had that condition, to a certain extent,
لقد مررت بتلك الحالة .. مما حفز التعاطف لدي الى مستوى معين
from my own childhood illness.
بسبب وعكتي الصحية في طفولتي
Eve Ensler, whom you'll hear later,
" إيف إنسلر " والتي سوف تتحدث لاحقاً
has had that condition activated
فُعّلت لديها خصلة التعاطف
amazingly in her
بصورة مميزة
through the various waters of suffering
عن طريق عدة انواع من المعاناة التي ترافقت معها
that she has been through.
التي مرت بها في حياتها
And what is fascinating
من الأمور الفاتنة
is that compassion has enemies,
ان للتعاطف اعداء
and those enemies are things like pity,
واحد اعداءه هو الشفقة
moral outrage,
الاساءات الاخلاقية
fear.
الخوف
And you know, we have a society, a world,
وكما تعلمون لدينا عالم .. ومجتمع
that is paralyzed by fear.
مقيد ومشلول بسبب الخوف
And in that paralysis, of course,
وفي هذا الشلل العام بالطبع
our capacity for compassion
فان قدرتنا على التعاطف
is also paralyzed.
تكون مقيدة ومشلولة ايضاً
The very word terror
ان كلمة إرهاب
is global.
باتت اليوم عالمية جداً
The very feeling of terror is global.
والخوف من الارهاب عالمي أيضاً
So our work, in a certain way,
لذا ان عملنا بصورة ما
is to address this imago,
يهدف الى معالجة هذه الفكرة
this kind of archetype
التي استشرت تماما
that has pervaded the psyche
بصورة " جنونية "
of our entire globe.
في عالمنا بأكمله
Now we know from neuroscience
نحن نعلم من علماء الاعصاب
that compassion has
ان التعاطف
some very extraordinary qualities.
لديه بعض الخاصيات المميزة به
For example:
على سبيل المثال
A person who is cultivating compassion,
ان الانسان المتعاطف والذي لديه درجة عالية من هذه الصفة
when they are in the presence of suffering,
عندما يواجه المعاناة امامه
they feel that suffering a lot more
فانه قد يشعر بالمعاناة
than many other people do.
اكثر من الاشخاص الذين يعانونها
However,
على كلٍ
they return to baseline a lot sooner.
انهم يعودن الى الوضع الطبيعي لهم اسرع من من يعانون من المعاناة حتماً
This is called resilience.
هذه تدعى المرونة
Many of us think that compassion drains us,
العديد من الاشخاص يظنون ان التعاطف يجر المآسي
but I promise you
ولكني اصدقكم القول
it is something that truly enlivens us.
انه في بعض الاحيان يفتح لنا أبواباً كبيرة
Another thing about compassion
وهناك شيء آخر عن التعاطف
is that it really enhances what's called neural integration.
انه فعلاً يحفز ويقوي التكامل العصبي
It hooks up all parts of the brain.
انه يصل بين كل اطراف الدماغ ويحفزها
Another, which has been discovered
وهو شيء تم اكتشافه من قبل
by various researchers
العديد من الباحثين
at Emory and at Davis and so on,
في جامعة أموري في منطقة دافيس ..
is that compassion enhances our immune system.
ان التعاطف يقوي جهاز المناعة
Hey,
نعم ..
we live in a very noxious world.
نحن نعيش في عالم مضطرب
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Most of us are shrinking
العديد منا يواجه المصاعب
in the face of psycho-social and physical poisons,
ونواجه مجتمع معقد وسموم فيزيائية
of the toxins of our world.
و العديد من السموم تحيط بنا
But compassion, the generation of compassion,
ولكن التعاطف ... جيل المتعاطفين
actually mobilizes
في الحقيقة .. يثبت
our immunity.
من مناعتنا
You know, if compassion is so good for us,
اتعلمون .. ان كان التعاطف امرٌ مفيد لنا
I have a question.
فلدي تساؤل ..
Why don't we train our children
لماذا لا نعلم اطفالنا
in compassion?
على التعاطف ؟
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
If compassion is so good for us,
ان كان التعاطف مفيداً بالنسبة لنا
why don't we train our health care providers in compassion
لماذا لا نقدم ضمن الضمان الصحي التعاطف كجزء من التأمينات الصحية
so that they can do what they're supposed to do,
لكي يحصل الانسان على ما يجب ان يحصل عليه
which is to really transform suffering?
والذي يمكنه فعلاً ان يقلل من معاناته
And if compassion is so good for us,
وان كان التعاطف جيداً لنا
why don't we vote on compassion?
لماذا لا نصوت للتعاطف
Why don't we vote for people in our government
لماذا لا ننتخب حكومتنا
based on compassion,
بناءا على التعاطف؟
so that we can have
لكي نحصل على عالم
a more caring world?
متعاطف اكثر فيما بينه
In Buddhism,
في الديانة البوذية
we say, "it takes a strong back and a soft front."
لدينا قول مفاده " ان الانسان يحتاج ظهراً قوياً ووجها لطيفاً "
It takes tremendous strength of the back
انك تحتاج قواعد قوية وصلبة
to uphold yourself in the midst of conditions.
لكي تصمد امام اعتى الظروف
And that is the mental quality of equanimity.
ولكي تحافظ على رباطة جأشك في وجه الصعاب
But it also takes a soft front --
ولكنك أيضاً تحتاج الوجه اللطيف
the capacity to really be open to the world as it is,
لكي تكون منفتحاً على العالم كما هو
to have an undefended heart.
ولكي تملك قلباً لا يُقهر
And the archetype of this in Buddhism
ان هذا المنحى في البوذية
is Avalokiteshvara, Kuan-Yin.
هو ل " أفالوكيتيشفارا , كوان ين "
It's a female archetype:
انها رمز انثوي
she who perceives
والتي تمثل
the cries of suffering in the world.
وجه المعاناة في العالم
She stands with 10,000 arms,
انها تملك 10،000 يد
and in every hand,
في كل يد
there is an instrument of liberation,
يوجد أداة محررة
and in the palm of every hand, there are eyes,
في راحة كل يد يوجد اعين
and these are the eyes of wisdom.
وهذه الاعين تمثل الحكمة
I say that, for thousands of years,
انا اقول .. انه ولمدة آلاف السنين
women have lived,
عاشت النساء
exemplified, met in intimacy,
وضربوا مثلاً والتقين في الحميمية
the archetype of Avalokitesvara,
ان رمز " أفالوكيتيشفارا "
of Kuan-Yin,
ل " كوان ين "
she who perceives
والتي تصور
the cries of suffering in the world.
وجه المعاناة في العالم
Women have manifested for thousands of years
ان النساء على مدى آلاف السنين مثلنّ
the strength arising from compassion
القوة الباذخة والتي ترمز للتعاطف
in an unfiltered, unmediated way
بصورة غير محدودة .. و غير مقيدة
in perceiving suffering
في عكس المعاناة
as it is.
كما هي
They have infused societies with kindness,
لقد حقنت النسوة المجتمعات بالرأفة
and we have really felt that
ونحن نشعر بهذا
as woman after woman
وكأنها رسالة نحملها من جيل
has stood on this stage
الى جيل عبر هذه الحياة .. ولقد خبرنا هذا على هذه المنصة
in the past day and a half.
على مدى اليوم ونصف اليوم الذي قضيناه في المؤتمر
And they have actualized compassion
ولقد جعلنا للتعاطف وجود فعلي
through direct action.
عبر العمل المباشر والافعال
Jody Williams called it:
لقد قالت جودي ويليمز
It's good to meditate.
انه من الجيد ان نتأمل !
I'm sorry, you've got to do a little bit of that, Jody.
آسفة .. يجب ان تقومي بالقليل من هذا يا جودي ..
Step back, give your mother a break, okay.
عودي خطوة للوراء .. وارحمي والدتك قليلاً
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
But the other side of the equation
ولكن الجزء الآخر من المعادلة
is you've got to come out of your cave.
هو انك ان اردت ان تخرج من كهفك
You have to come into the world
عليك ان تواجه العالم
like Asanga did,
كما فعل أسانغا
who was looking to realize Maitreya Buddha
والذي كان يسعى لإدراك " ماريتا بوذا "
after 12 years sitting in the cave.
فاعتكف في الكهف 12 عاماً ولم يتجلى له " ماريتا بوذا "
He said, "I'm out of here."
ففقد الامل وخرج من الكهف
He's going down the path.
وهو في طريق عودته
He sees something in the path.
رأى شيئاً جذب انتباهه
He looks, it's a dog, he drops to his knees.
انه كلب .. لقد وقع على ركبتيه ..
He sees that the dog has this big wound on its leg.
شاهد ان الكلب مصاب اصابة بليغة
The wound is just filled with maggots.
وكان الجرح مليئ بالديدان
He puts out his tongue
فوضع فلسانه
in order to remove the maggots,
لكي يزيل تلك الديدان
so as not to harm them.
لكي لا يؤذي الديدان
And at that moment,
وفي تلك اللحظة
the dog transformed
تحوّل الكلب
into the Buddha of love and kindness.
إلى بوذا الحب والرحمة وتجلى له
I believe
انا أؤمن
that women and girls today
ان النساء والبنات
have to partner in a powerful way with men --
عليهم ان يشاركوا الرجل بصورة حقيقية
with their fathers,
ان يشاركوا آبائهم
with their sons, with their brothers,
وابنائهم .. واخوانهم
with the plumbers, the road builders,
وصانعي الطرق .. والسباكون ..
the caregivers, the doctors, the lawyers,
والاطباء والمهندسون والمحامون
with our president,
والرؤساء
and with all beings.
وكل المخلوقات
The women in this room
ان النسوة هنا في هذه القاعة
are lotuses in a sea of fire.
هن كزهرة اللوتس في بحر من نيران
May we actualize that capacity
وعليها ان تدرك قدرتها على مساعدة
for women everywhere.
النساء حول العالم
Thank you.
شكراً لكم
(Applause)
(تصفيق)